Finding Aid for Committee on Student Discipline (University of Michigan) records, 1914-1961
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Committee on Student Discipline (University of Michigan) records 1914-1961, 1922-1961
University of Michigan. Committee on Student Discipline.
4.5 linear feet
87112 Bimu C15 2
The Committee on Student Discipline records document how the University of Michigan set non-academic student policy and how it enforced those policies during the early and mid twentieth century. The collection includes records created by the Committee on Student Discipline, the Subcommittee on Student Discipline, the Committee on Student Conduct, and the Joint Judiciary Council, and contains records from individual student cases and correspondence dealing with university policy.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (Donor No. 2948 ) was received in one accession, 1969.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Committee on Student Discipline (University of Michigan) records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Committee on Student Discipline (University of Michigan) records record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 1-4
The Regents of the University of Michigan, upon the recommendation of the University Senate, formed the Committee on Student Discipline in June of 1922. Consisting of members appointed by college deans and the university president, the jurisdiction of the committee included cases of impropriety involving male students that attended more than one college or school within the university, or cases referred to the committee by the dean of that student's college. "The decisions of the University Committee on discipline are final in all cases, but the President of the University shall be consulted (whenever practicable) before any final action is taken resulting in suspension or expulsion" (Board of Regents Proceedings, 1922, pg. 506). At that time, the Dean of Women handled cases involving female students.
In 1934, the university changed the name of the Committee on Student Discipline to the Committee on Student Conduct. While its membership remained the same, the new committee was "charged with the task of formulating and interpreting principles of conduct..." (Board of Regents Proceedings, 1934, pg. 353). The Committee on Student Conduct formed a Subcommittee on Discipline to adjudicate specific cases of misconduct. The subcommittee was comprised of staff appointed by the chair of the committee. The subcommittee invited students from the Men's Student Council and the Michigan League to meetings, but these student participants did not receive a vote.
In the 1950s, the Committee on Student Conduct formed the Joint Judiciary Council, which combined judicial bodies that had previously been separated by gender. The council was comprised of members chosen by the student body leadership and outgoing council staff, and had the power to hear cases and recommend disciplinary action. After its formation, the Joint Judiciary Council took over the adjudication role of the Subcommittee of Student Discipline, hearing cases and enforcing penalties while acting under the subcommittee's authority. The subcommittee rarely met after the Joint Judiciary Council's establishment.
During the 1960s, calls for more student involvement in university policy, campus unrest, and perceived lawlessness led to great changes in the university judicial system. In 1963, the Committee on Student Conduct was replaced with the University Committee on Standards and Conduct, and it seems the Subcommittee on Student Discipline also ceased to exist around this time. The Joint Judiciary Council continued to perform it duties until 1970, when demands for a larger student role led to the formation of the University Council, which was created to formulate and propose regulations governing student conduct. This new body was part of a complete overhaul of the non-academic judicial system and the formation of a new university wide Code of Conduct.
The Committee on Student Discipline records measure 4.75 linear feet and range from 1914-1961, the bulk of which spans 1922-1961. This collection is arranged in two series: Student Discipline Committees and Approved Social Events.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Office of Student Affairs.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; University of Michigan. Committee on Student Discipline.
- Student Discipline Committees
  The Student Discipline Committees series, 1914, 1922-1961 (4.5 linear feet) consist of correspondence, meeting minutes, hearing records, and reports pertaining to the formation of non-academic student policy and enforcement. Most of these records are bound and arranged chronologically. The records are produced by the Committee and Subcommittee on Student Discipline, the Committee on Student Conduct, and the Joint Judiciary Council. A large portion of these records include details of individual student cases, and are therefore subject to student educational records restrictions. Of particular interest are the records that show how the university exercised its judicial authority (records from the 1920s and 30s are unrestricted given the expiration of the student records restriction), and the volume labeled "University Committee on Student Conduct," which contains higher level policy documents from the Committee on Student Discipline and the Committee on Student Conduct. Researchers should note that differentiating between records created by the different committees can be confusing, due to similar names and overlapping functions of committees. Also note that bound records are titled with the name of a single committee, but could include records from several.
  - University Committee on Student Conduct 1914, 1922-1948 (Box 1)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2023 ]
  - University Committee on Student Discipline
    - 1934-1938 (Box 1)
    - 1938-1946 (Box 1)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2021 ]
    - 1946-1947 (Box 1)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2022 ]
    - 1947-1948 (Box 1)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 1)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2024 ]
    - 1949-1950 (Box 2)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2025 ]
  - University Subcommittee on Student Discipline
    - 1950-1951 (Box 2)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2026 ]
    - 1951-1952 (Box 2)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2027 ]
    - 1952-1953 (Box 2)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2028 ]
    - 1953-1954 (Box 3)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2029 ]
    - 1955-1955 (Box 3)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2030 ]
  - University Committee on Student Discipline
    - 1955-1956 (Box 3)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2031 ]
    - 1956-1957 (Box 3)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2032 ]
    - 1957-1958 (Box 4)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2033 ]
    - 1958-1959 (Box 4)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2034 ]
    - 1959-1960 (Box 4)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2035 ]
    - 1960-1961 (Box 4)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2036 ]
  - Hearings 1921-1922 (Box 5)
  - Case of Louis T. Orr Hazing/Case of Andrew Greer 1922 (Box 5)
  - Meeting Minutes 1923-1924 (Box 5)
  - University Committee on Student Discipline 1923-1933 (Box 5)
  - Report of the University Committee on Student Discipline circa 1924 (Box 5)
- Approved Social Events
  The Approved Social Events series, 1939-1954 (.25 linear feet) is comprised of two bound volumes listing the university approved events and sponsors.
  - 1939-1948 (Box 5)
  - 1948-1954 (Box 5)